<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A politike discourse most excellent for this time present: composed by a French gentleman, against those of the League, which went about to perswade the King to breake the allyance with England, and to confirme it with Spaine</title>
            <title>Discours politique, tres-excellent pour le temps present. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02962</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856053</idno>
  <idno type="VID">21569</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240857518</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 13101</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S120860</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99856053e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02962)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21569)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 304:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A politike discourse most excellent for this time present: composed by a French gentleman, against those of the League, which went about to perswade the King to breake the allyance with England, and to confirme it with Spaine</title>
                  <title>Discours politique, tres-excellent pour le temps present. English.</title>
                  <author>Marquino, Francesco.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27 [i.e. 41], [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn VVoolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Gentil-homme francois.  Discours politique, tres-excellent pour le temps present.</note>
                  <note>Translator's note "To the discrete and vertuous reader" signed: Francis Mar., i.e. Francesco Marquino.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A discourse of the league, betweene France and England.</note>
                  <note>P. 41 misnumbered 27.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  History --  Henry III, 1574-1589 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21569:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21569:1"/>
            <p>A Politike Discourse most excellent for this time present: <hi>Composed by a French Gentleman,</hi> against those of the League, which went about to perswade the King to breake the Allyance with England, and to confirme it with Spaine.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by Iohn Woolfe, 1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21569:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21569:2"/>
            <head>To the discrete and vertuous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Author of this worke is a stranger, whose loue of truth; hath ouercome in him the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall loue of his countrie, in composing it. The translator is a stranger likewise, whose loue of true religion and this blessed Realme hath mooued him to translate it. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors intention was, to manifest the great difference between the English and the Spanish Nations, to the intent his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie might thereupon make a iust choice for hir benefite and vtilitie. The translator his meaning is, to publish it, to the intent the whole world may know &amp; vnderstand, that great difference. For although the Spaniard be greater in lande, and thereupon maketh great boastings and brags, yet is he to be cōpared to the Cipresse tree, the which though it be high, great and faire in sight, is neuerthelesse, weake, tender, slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and vnfruitfull. The Englishman contrariwise, though he be lesser in Land, keepeth himselfe humbly thereupon, safe, still, quiet, and wise: and is therefore to be compared to the Oliue tree, lowe, faire, strong, fruitfull, and most abundant. The third and last consideration of the Author, is grounded vpon a farre better cause than any worldly commodities, &amp; that is the contemplation of spirituall qualities which are to be reaped in England, and not in Spaine, as euery man will confesse that is indifferent in matters of religion. I say not this to flatter in praysing and exalting England in or before his owne face: but because I beleeue it, and know it to be so. For how can the Spanishmen say, as the Englishmen may say with saint <hi>Paul, God is with vs,</hi> and againe, <hi>If God be with vs, who can be against vs.</hi> We haue seene the last som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer by experience the true effects of this which I speake now.</p>
            <p>Therefore I as translator ioyne willingly with the Author, and do conclude with this preface, as hee doth with his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course:
<pb facs="tcp:21569:3"/>and say that the Spanish nation, is at hir highest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and shalt therefore no more ascende but descend: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause she goeth about not only to take and inuade hir neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours countries, but she dare say, she will haue the fist Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, that only appertaineth to Iesus Christ, who will giue it to whom it pleaseth him, and will not giue it vnto them: but I dare say he will giue it vnto Englishmen, which haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him, and he wil be with them still so long as they liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his holy will.</p>
            <p>I do not speake of things done this day, yesterday, or the day before, but by experience and obseruation of yeares more than one score. Therefore if England doth consider the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, the strength, the good, or euill will of his enimies, he will beginne to perceiue what I meane, and say as I say. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine if he entred into consideration of the great number &amp; strong benefites which the Almightie God hath doone vnto him through his mercie and good will, vnder the blessed protection (of his most precious maide seruant, his most ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and deare nurse of his Church) our most gratious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Queene Elizabeth, he will say as I say. I can go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnlesse. I would make of my preface a discourse, which should be out of my purpose: I will therfore conclude with my prayers, and beseech the Almightie God to defende from all enemies his holy vniuersall Church, the Queenes Maiestie, hir most honorable Councell, this blessed Realme and people, and keepe vs all in peace in Christ our Lord, so be it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Francis Mar.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:21569:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A proofe, that the friendship and league with</hi> England, is more behoofefull to France, then the League of Spaine.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ylla</hi> (a Romane Captaine) inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to perswade <hi>Bocchus</hi> to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying,<note place="margin">Salust, in the warres of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurth.</note> which hee practised, of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurth,</hi> grounded chiefely his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion vpon this point, that a man had neuer friends enough. A thing which common and ordinarie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience maketh so sensible, both to our feeling, &amp; to our sight, that whosoeuer would call in question, or impugne that case, shoulde but shewe himselfe voide of iudgement, and common sense. Therefore it is, that in our French language, there is this common prouerbe: that he which hath a good neighbor, hath a good morning: aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing vs thereby, that hee which mainteineth himselfe well with his neighbors, hath taken the best way that he coulde deuise, for the estate of his particular businesse.</p>
            <p>For as there is nothing more grieuous for a man, than to see himselfe pinched by those, at whose hande hee loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for fauour and comfort in his aduersitie. So is there no greater contentment, than to see himselfe so well ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and cherished of his neighbours, as it may bee a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of his good behauiour among them. The which thing considered, those learned men,<note place="margin">Hesiodus in his booke of workes and dayes.</note> that by their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings haue traced vs out the way of vertue, haue made so great account of the regard that is due to good neighbors, that in some respect, they haue preferred it before the same which is due vnto kinsfolke and allyes. That great and wise Captaine <hi>Themistocles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicero in his first booke of dueties.</note> shewed sometimes to haue right well vnderstood this point: for causing one of his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21569:4"/>inheritances to bee solde by the cryer, hee commaunded him to say, and proclaime it alowde (to the intent, hee might put it to greater prise,) that it was well neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Nowe, if in particular thinges, the respect of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood ought to bee in such recommendation to vs: how much more I pray you, ought it so to doo, in the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing of matters of state? Who is so ignorant a man, of the affaires of this worlde, that hee knoweth not howe the neighbourhoode of the <hi>Bulgarians,</hi> caused the ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and descending of the <hi>Turke</hi> into <hi>Greece,</hi> and opened them the way to serse vppon that which they holde at this day in <hi>Europe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like may bee saide, in the same regard of <hi>Italie:</hi> for the astaires of the <hi>Ʋenctians, Florentines, Geneuoies,</hi> and <hi>Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politans,</hi> were not troubled, but by the malice of one of their neighbours: to wit, <hi>Lewis Sforce,</hi> vsurper of the state of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine:</hi> who for the satisfying of his owne priuate affections, made no conscience to trouble the quiet state, which <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> had so long enioyed by the wisedome of <hi>Laurence</hi> of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis:</hi> and to make his countrie a pray to the wars and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences of the French-men.</p>
            <p>On the contrarie part, if we regard neerely the state of things past, we shall finde, that manie of the greatest hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of <hi>Germanie,</hi> haue beene by the good foresight, and heartie affection of their neighbours, preserued from the ouerturning, wherewith the common rage menaced them. In the time of our fathers: to wit, in the yeare of our Lord, 1504. <hi>Philip</hi> Conte <hi>Palatine,</hi> fell at variance with the Emperor <hi>Maximilian;</hi> and hauing the end of his case, as little prosperitie, as the enterprise thereof had right: hee was outlawed by the states of the Empire, and brought to a great perplexitie.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Frederike,</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> his next neighbour, a Prince of great wit and skill, handled this matter so milde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, that all the storme turned into a calme, and pleasant tranquilitie. Wherein, notwithstanding, I thinke not, that Princes can pretend any aduantage vpon the states of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stocratie and popularitie. All men know, how that about fourtie yeares past, <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Sanoy</hi> inuaded <hi>Geneua:</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21569:4"/>the possession and dominion whereof, hee had left to his successors, if they of <hi>Frybourge,</hi> being neighbors and allya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Geneuians, had not made him to leaue off, and to let go his pray, which hee had as it were betweene his teeth.</p>
            <p>I alleage these familiar examples, and of fresh date, least I shoulde rest too much vppon those of olde time: and speciallie of the common weale of <hi>Athens,</hi> who alwayes professed to releeue their neighbors, that were cast downe by anie hard ouerthrowe. Whereof the setting vp againe of <hi>Thebes,</hi> will serue for a sufficient recorde and witnesse, so long as mans life shall haue the good happe to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned with the light of good learning. Thus may you see then, verie pertinent reasons, to make vs to vnderstand howe carefullie the states and gouernements ought to be vnderpropped with the friendship and faithfulnesse of their neighbours. But forasmuch as this is a point of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, so it required a deepe and ripe consideration: for men which are lesse experimented and practised in worldly affaires, doo suffer themselues so much the more easily to be deceiued: specially when vaine outward shewe can apparell and decke her selfe, with the glittering glose of substantiall profite.</p>
            <p>And to manifest the matter by example, and by the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe of one particular deede, to open the way to the deciding of a generalitie, I will speake of that which more neerely concerned the disposement of our owne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. There is no man so blinde, of any vnderstanding, which doth not see and perceiue the poore and misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble state wherein the Realme of <hi>France,</hi> hauing lost his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient beautie, is nowe brought at this day, by the long continuance and sharpenesse of ciuill warres. All men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse that shee hath neede of a restoratiue to recouer her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine from so dangerous a disease: neuerthelesse all do not agree vpon the confection, and the ingredients that are now fit and sortable to such a restoratiue. But yet so it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out, that those which by reason of their dealings in worldly affaires, haue attained to a greater experience than other, do come vnto this point: that according vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21569:5"/>the order of good Phisitions, the disease is to bee cured by his contraries. And therefore, in as much as the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease of <hi>France</hi> proceedeth but of vnquietnesse: that there is no better way to establish her againe in her former state of health, than a good and sure rest: an aduice in my iudgement, much better grounded in reason, than plainely discoursed. And that it is so, when question is concerning the quieting of our countrie: that man were too farre ouerseene, which woulde inclose it within the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of <hi>France:</hi> hauing no farther regarde or care, howe farre shee were at oddes, or howe shee fared with her neighbours, so the inhabitantes of the Realme may liue in peace among themselues, and that the fire of ciuill wars be quenched.</p>
            <p>And although, I must roundly confesse, that they being brought vppon the falling into the one of the two incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences: there is no forraine warre, howe harde and daungerous soeuer it bee, which ought not to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, if by the same countrie it may bee saued from ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill warre: yet notwithstanding, the full and perfite pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritie of a state consisted in being exempted from both those inconueniences: vnlesse wee doo esteeme our age to bee priuiledged with such a fauour, that wee may haue warre without the appertenances thereof: that is to wit, without miserie and pouertie. They then which procure the quietnesse and welfare of our <hi>France,</hi> must aime at this marke, that not onely all ciuill broiles bee quenched, but also that shee mainteine her selfe in good order with her neighbours. And speciallie with those, whose ally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is most commodious, and most assured vnto her: which is a point in my iudgement, as needefull to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, as hard to be decided, by reason of the diuersitie of mens affections: and of those which professe to preferre their owne peculiar profite, before the welfare and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of the common weale.</p>
            <p>But yet, if in the handling of this matter, we doo bring none other passion with vs, than the earnest loue of trueth, and of our owne natiue countrie, there would be no great a doo in discussing of this difficultie. And doo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21569:5"/>not thinke (all account made and rebated, whether it bee considered whole togither, or whether there bee had any particular respect to the present time) that there be any of our neighbours, whereof the alliance be so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious and behoofefull to vs, as the same of the English<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. And on the other side, I am of opinion, that he which in matters of state, would treate of the common errors, could not chose a fairer argument, than to show that those which ordinarily do call the Englishmen, the ancient ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the state and crowne of <hi>France,</hi> meaning to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase to themselues estimation of learning among the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, do discouer themselues vtterly ignorant among the learned. And because many Courtiers whome I haue heard discourse of this matter proceede so farre, that they preferre the allyance with <hi>Spaine</hi> before all others, hauing (as they say) a speciall regarde to the benefite and welfare of <hi>France,</hi> I will debate that question, which in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath no better grounde than partiall affection, or on too much superficiall knowledge of the affaires of this worlde. I hope therefore to show by apparant reason, that the alliance with <hi>England</hi> is to vs much more behoofefull, than the allyance with <hi>Spaine:</hi> and by the selfe same means to auoide the generall proposition, and to proue that there is no people in the worlde, whose allyaunce is so commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and necessarie for vs, as those or <hi>England.</hi> And to lay a foundation to mine opinion, I say that whensoeuer que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion is to be had of allyaunce with any people, regard is to be had chiefely of two thinges: the one, that those whose allyaunce wee preferre, may haue the most occasions and meanes to succour vs: the other, that they haue likewise most meanes to annoy vs, being become our enimies. And which is (I pray you) the people in the worlde, which hath iuster cause to loue vs than the Englishmē? who is so allyed to vs in bloud, conformable in conditions, and brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in vertuous inclinations? the which I vnderstande not only to say of the Englishmen, whom we so call at this day, but also of the ancient Britaines, of whom there is yet to be seene a remnant in the country of Walles: who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing they resemble in manners, customes, and vsages
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21569:6"/>the other people of Englande, yet doo they differ from them in language.<note place="margin">Caesar in his first booke of his warres in Gallia.</note>
               <hi>Iulius Caesar,</hi> who was the first amongest the Romane Captaines that discouered, and had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the state of this Ile: teaching vs, that that one part of the Britains, which bordered vpon the sea, tooke their originall from the Lowe Countries of <hi>Germanie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caesar in his second booke of his warres in Gallia.</note> the same Author hath left vnto vs in writing, that in his time the king of <hi>Soyssons</hi> named <hi>Diuitiacus,</hi> had also commanded to the state of great Britaine: and therefore it is no maruell, though the Britaines, (especially those which inhabite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Kent) did agree in humanitie, and in manners of life, with the Gauls.</p>
            <p>And indeede, if we will take the right thereof by that we finde in writing, none can be said to be more brotherlike, than these two nations. And without proceeding so farre, as to search out euery point by himselfe, I will speake only of the <hi>Druydes,</hi> who had in olde time the handling of all matters in both these Nations.</p>
            <p>These <hi>Druydes</hi> were Poetes and Priestes, as there was in old time one <hi>Hesiodus</hi> in <hi>Greece.</hi> It is a certaine thing that the first among the Grecians which innobled their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie with the knowledge of learning, cōprehended all their doctrinè in verses: as <hi>Homerus, Hesiodus, Orpheus, Musaeus, Linus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch in the life of Thaeseus.</note>
               <hi>Empedocles, Parmenides:</hi> yea and euen <hi>Pitheus,</hi> of whom <hi>Plutarch</hi> maketh mention. In respect whereof <hi>Plato</hi> attributed so much vnto Poets, that he called them the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and chiefest of wisedome. For the <hi>Druydes,</hi> were also Mathematicians and Philosophers:<note place="margin">Plato in his Lycidas. Cicero in his second booke of the nature of the Goddes</note> which is the cause that I cannot well conceiue what <hi>Cicero</hi> meant, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Britaines and Scythians together, in respect of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the Mathematicall arts.</p>
            <p>If he referred him to the record of his familiar friend <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batius,</hi> euery one knoweth to haue beene such a witnes (as may be gathered out of <hi>Cicero</hi> his own writings) that liked better to behold a storehouse of victuals, thā the cōtempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the starres. But it seemeth that <hi>Cicero,</hi> which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise was a man of exquisite iudgement, would verifie the saying of <hi>Thales</hi> the <hi>Milesian,</hi> who beeing demaunded of, howe much the truth is different from the vntruth: euen
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21569:6"/>as much (quoth he) as the eyes from the eares: likewise may we say in respect of the matter that we haue in hande, that we finde eyes in <hi>Caesar,</hi> and eares in <hi>Cicero.</hi> Now whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Britaines tooke the knowledge of learning from the Galles, or the Galles from the Britaines: so much it is, that the youngmen of <hi>Gauland,</hi> (for the more furtherance of their studies transported them into <hi>Britaine</hi> vnto the <hi>Druydes</hi> of that countrie, at whose handes they learned the most hidden secrets of Philosophie, and of Mathematicall sciences. If we will stande to the report of <hi>Caesars</hi> writinges thereof, the Philosophie and doctrine of the <hi>Druydes</hi> had his beginning in great <hi>Britaine:</hi> which opinion I willingly imbrace, notwithstanding, that the excellent and rare learned man <hi>Petrus Ramus,</hi> seemeth to holde the contrarie in some writings of his. Therefore it is no maruell,<note place="margin">Ramus in his booke of the manners of ancient Gauls.</note> though so learned a Nation, and so well trayned in good sciences, hath beene indewed with an humanitie answerable to their skill, and whereof our <hi>Gaulles</hi> haue reaped the chiefe fruite thereof. In so much that <hi>Caesar</hi> being about to passe ouer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Britaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caesar in his fourth booke of his watres in Gallia.</note> brought forth no other pretence of his voyage thether, but only that the <hi>Gaulles</hi> had bin succoured of the <hi>Britains</hi> in all the quarrels which they had to deale against the <hi>Romanes.</hi> And if any man thinke that the people which since <hi>Caesaers</hi> time, haue seised the coūtries of <hi>Gallia &amp; Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> that is to say, the Englishmen &amp; Frenchmen, haue beene knit in looser friendship, or haue lesse cause of mutual inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining one an other, he deceiued himselfe as much as hee that is ignorant, how great force is in friendship grounded vpon naturall alliance, whereof the remembrance can not be buried, neyther by processe of time, nor distance of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The Citizens of <hi>Sais</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> sayd that their citie was founded by the Goddesse <hi>Minerua,</hi> as so likewise did the <hi>Athenians.</hi> In consideration of which allyance, as <hi>Plato</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessed, the <hi>Greekes</hi> generally, and the <hi>Athenians</hi> specially,<note place="margin">Plato in his Timaeus.</note> were welcome, and very much made of at <hi>Sais.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it remaineth to be considered, howe straightly the Frenchmen are vnited with the Englishmen, and what show of friendshippe they haue made at all times, the one vnto the other: neither is it to be sayde, that they haue
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21569:7"/>had great and long warres betwixt them, yea euen within the remembrance of our great grandfathers.</p>
            <p>For by that reason, we must banish friendshippe from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all nations of the earth: and by the selfesame reason we must conclude, that there can be no friendshippe euen among the Frenchmen themselues, the which of late daies haue set vp in their owne countrie, a scafolde of the blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diest tragedie that euer was heard of. And as touching the warres betweene the Englishmen and the Frenchmen, I hope to show hereafter in dewe place, that so farre it is that that consideration ought to bring any alteration to the friendship betweene them &amp; vs, that in contrarie, it ought rather to he a verie strong inducement vnto vs, to ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der some increase of goodwill on our parts towards them. For God hauing giuen them so great aduantages ouer vs, as euery one knowes, it is harde to be saide, whether that noble nation hath shewed hir selfe more valiant in battaile, than milde and gentle after the victorie. Much lesse are to the purpose the rude speeches which may be heard in the streetes, as well in <hi>France</hi> as in <hi>Englande,</hi> as among others are these english wordes, Cullion, Frenchdogge: which is the rethoricke of pedlers, coblers, beggars, and other peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the like stampe, and not the speeches of the honest, and ciuill sort, whereof wee intende to speake in this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course: leauing aside all these toyes, let vs speake of the kindely amitie that is betweene these two Nations. In the time of the Emperour <hi>Martian</hi> and <hi>Ʋalentinian,</hi> about the yeare of Christ, 449. <hi>Witigerne</hi> King of great <hi>Britaine,</hi> being in will to beate backe the Picts and Scots, called to his aide the Angles or Englishmen, who at that time dwelt among the Vites and Saxons: and indeede the Welchmen do still at this day call the Englishmen, Sasses, as if one would say, Saxons, the which hath beene told me for a certainetie by some learned men of that countrie. It followeth then vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this discourse, that the Englishmen are come of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes, as also are the Frenchmen, according as our Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians do report. And although, that as touching the french Nation, I dare not vpholde that they are descended of the Saxons: yet notwithstanding, the house of the kings, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21569:7"/>at this day cōmandeth in <hi>France,</hi> fetched his originall from thence, as they can tell which haue the most perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the historie. For <hi>Windekinde</hi> a Saxon, of the line of the great <hi>Windekind</hi> subdued by <hi>Charlemayne,</hi> came into <hi>France</hi> to the succor of <hi>Charles</hi> the balde, which was greatly disquieted of the <hi>Normans:</hi> This younger <hi>Windekind,</hi> had a sonne named <hi>Robert,</hi> who so fortunately followed the foot steps of his father, that <hi>Charles</hi> the bald made him generall of the armie which he sent against the <hi>Normans:</hi> who at that time spoiled <hi>France.</hi> This <hi>Robert</hi> was flaine in battel leauing a son named <hi>Otho,</hi> who by consent of the Emperor <hi>Arnold,</hi> had the gouernement of <hi>France,</hi> during the minoritle of <hi>Charles</hi> the simple. By the which gouernment neuertheles, he purchased not so great reputatiō, as he did in being the father of <hi>Hugh</hi> the great Earle of <hi>Paris.</hi> But <hi>Hugh Capot</hi> the sonne of this <hi>Hugh</hi> the great, surmounted the glorie, and renowme of all the aforesayde, as well for making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe the chiefest of the absolute state and gouernement of <hi>France,</hi> as for leauing a kingly posteritie behinde him, the which stil at this day is yet vpright, deuided into two hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, that is to wit, of <hi>Valoys</hi> and of <hi>Bourbon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so wee may conclude, that although the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the Englishmen,<note place="margin">Aristotle in his first booke of his matters of state. Cap. 1.</note> can not be sayde (according to the terme of <hi>Charondas</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to say, liuing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: or according to <hi>Epimenides,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as if one would say, nourished at one selfe same fire or householde, or as we say in French, men beeing together at pot, and at borde: yet notwithstanding, they may well bee called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to say, comming of one stocke. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, that this allyaunce bee of it selfe ynough clarified in the histories: yet is it yet better by conformitie or agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ablenesse of the conditions of these two peoples, and by good behauiour of the one towardes the other. The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishmen euen as the Frenchmen are generous, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently (as <hi>Aristotle</hi> teacheth) farre from dissimulation,<note place="margin">Aristotle in his fourth booke of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie. Cap. 3.</note> hating, or louing openly, gouerning themselues more by truth, than by opinion, louing a great deale more the deed than the showe, free in his speech, desirous of libertie, easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgetting the wrong to them done: and moreouer he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21569:8"/>is liberall, ciuill, curteous and gentle: of all vertuous qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, I belecue there are to be found as many cleere &amp; eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent testimonies, as there be sentences spoken of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploytes in historiographers that are not partiall. For as concerning their ciuility, what better witnes therof can we haue then <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Commines,</hi> who had the experience ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of himselfe in the behalfe of the lorde of <hi>Ʋancler.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip of Commes.</note> I should speake of a thing too much renowmed ouer all the world, if I should spende too many words in discoursing of their magnificence &amp; liberalitie. Certainely if it be true that <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodian</hi> hath written concerning barbarous men, namely that they are naturally desirous of money,<note place="margin">Herodian in the life of the Emperour Commodus.</note> the Englishmen are sufficiently discharged of the blame of barbarousnesse: notwithstanding that some writers being eyther ignorant, or ouermuch partiall, doo disgrace them in that respect. And what neede I to stande long vpon this point, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that the experience, and record of most noble, and excellent personages, do openly ratisie my sayinges. The late <hi>Ʋidame</hi> of <hi>Charires</hi> (who being one of the most liberall noble men of our time, could best speake of liberalitie) said openly, that if there were any Nation in Christendome, more liberall and courteous towarde strangers, than Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishmen are, he was contented to be registred among such as speake vnaduisedly of things they know not. The <hi>Vidame</hi> that succeeded him as wel in his vertues, as in his heritage, protested oftentimes, that he durst not speak of the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, curtesie, &amp; liberalitie of Englishmen, for feare least he should breake open a discourse, whereinto he might more easily enter, thā find the way out againe. <hi>Odet</hi> the Cardinall of <hi>Chastilion,</hi> had ordinarily this saying in his mouth, that courtesie had in olde time inclosed her selfe within <hi>France,</hi> but now it was passed ouer the sea.</p>
            <p>This matter would require a longer discourse: but I am a Frenchman, and iealous of the honour of my countrie. <hi>Plutarch</hi> did write,<note place="margin">Plutarch in the life of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero.</note> that the great Rethoritian <hi>Molon,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one day heard <hi>Cicero</hi> declaiming in Greeke, saide with lamentation, that he bewayled the state of <hi>Greece,</hi> for that <hi>Cicero</hi> should carrie away the greatest ornament thereof, namely the cloquence. For mine owne part, although I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21569:8"/>be as greatly affectioned towardes Englishmen, as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertes of their vertue requireth, yet doth it greeueth me to see them so enriched with our spoyles. Insomuch that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> may at this day, euen of good right, be termed a verie Sanctuarie of all ciuilitie, kindnesse, and courtesie: whereof may be seen the presidents, not only towards their friends, in the time of peace, but also towards their enimies in time of war. Of many examples, I will choose one so notable, as I can not tell whether the like can any where be found in the histories eyther of Greekes or Latins. Among all the battels, that euer were fought in <hi>France,</hi> the battell of <hi>Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers</hi> is most memorable, not onely for the inestimable losse of them that were vanquished, but also much more for the courtesie and gentlenesse of the Conquerours. For the Nobilitie of <hi>Fraunce</hi> were there hewen in peeces, many Princes and great Lordes were taken prisoners, and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the King <hi>John</hi> himselfe fell into the hands of the Prince of Wales, who anon after conueyed him into <hi>Englande,</hi> where he receiued so fauourable and friendly intertayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of King <hi>Edwarde</hi> father to the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> that he being suffered, vpon his faith, and vpon hostages, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into <hi>France,</hi> to set order in his affaires, afterwarde hauing aduisedly considered the intertainement that had beene done vnto him, he found so sweete taste and sauour, in the English courtesie, that he esteemed it more for his honour, to die by so gratious a Prince, than to liue as king of the greatest and mightiest kingdome of Christendome. <hi>Porus</hi> a king of <hi>India,</hi> being taken prisoner by great <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> and being asked of him what intertainement hee looked to receiue, I am a king (quoth he) deale with me like a king. <hi>Alexander</hi> making a stay thereat, and asking him, if hee desired nothing else: this woorde king-like (sayeth he) comprehendeth all. Whereuppon <hi>Alexander</hi> had him in great estimation afterwarde, and vsed him as he had required. But this courtesie of king <hi>Edwarde</hi> ought to be esteemed so much more greater than <hi>Alexanders,</hi> for so much as <hi>Porus</hi> had not taken the armes, but beeing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained for his owne lawfull defence, whereas contrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, king Iohn would not accept the honorable condition
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21569:9"/>of peace, which the prince of <hi>Wales</hi> offered vnto him, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer the Cardinall of <hi>Perigort,</hi> being sent frō the Pope <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> declared vnto him, to moue him to any cōpositiō: but suffering himselfe to be ouermastred by his own choler, he was vanquished by a handfull of men, &amp; lost such a battell on the 19. day of September 1356, as cannot be matched by any other, than by that so much renowmed battell of <hi>Cannas,</hi> which was like to haue ouerturned the whole state of the <hi>Romane</hi> cōmon-weale. And although the ciuill wars be ordinarily hādled with so much more a poisoned mind, as the alliance is straighter betwixt thē that are of one coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie: yet notwithstanding, if credite may be giuē to the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories, there shal not be foūd any natiō in the world, which in that behalfe be in such &amp; so long a possessiō of modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō,<note place="margin">Comines in his 112. chap.</note> &amp; mercifulnes, as the English Nation. <hi>Comines</hi> who had as much, or more experience of the doings of <hi>England,</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Frenchman of his time, sayth that in ciuill wars the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of that country is, to come out of hand to the battel, &amp; that the chiefe of the part to which the victory inclineth, causeth to be proclaimed a loud, <hi>Saue the people.</hi> And would to God, that we had vsed the like moderation &amp; mildnesse in our ciuill wars, for then should we haue yet at this day fiftie thousande witnesses of our discention, whose bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed dooth nowe prouoke Gods wrath against our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of <hi>France.</hi> Howbeit, for as much as the occasion of loue towardes a Nation, whether it be by naturall affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or by conformitie of manners, is not a thing that of it selfe deserueth great commendation, vnlesse it be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested by indeuour to bring it to passe: the processe of our discourse requireth to haue this point more narrowly searched, to the ende, that such as call the Englishmen the auncient enemies to the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> may learne, eyther to speake better, or else to holde their peace all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and say nothing, when such matters come in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion. I say therefore that the effectes of friendshippe haue beene at all times mutualy vsed betweene both these Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. For leauing a side that which I haue alleadged of <hi>Casar,</hi> where hee writeth that the <hi>Britaines</hi> had succoured the <hi>Gaulles</hi> in all their warres against him.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21569:9"/>
            <p> I will take presidents of later remembrance: that is to say, since one hundred or sixe score yeares past. In the time of king <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleuenth, <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgoine</hi> being desirous to clip the wings of the same <hi>Lewis</hi> his deadly foe, called to his aide <hi>Edward</hi> king of <hi>England,</hi> his brother in Law, who needed not to be drawen by the eares, to make an entrie into <hi>France:</hi> whervnto he wanted no pretence. By reason whereof; there was then great likelihood, that if the Duke of <hi>Burgoyne</hi> coulde haue skilled to wield his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritie, he had either ouerthrowne, or at the least, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shaken the whole state of <hi>France.</hi> The saide king <hi>Lewis,</hi> being a prince of more wisedome than hardinesse, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to what an inconuenience his affaires were brought, wrought so by policie, that a treatie of peace with king <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> was had, which was done at <hi>Piquignie.</hi> And it may well be said, that then the gentlenesse of king <hi>Edward</hi> stood <hi>France</hi> in steede of a great and strong bulwarke, against the violence and heady force of the Burgonians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the eight, the sonne and successour of the saide <hi>Lewis,</hi> was so farre fauored from heauen, as to haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion offered him to requite the said courtesie towards the English nation: and hee was as readie to imbrace such an occasion, as it was happily offered vnto him. <hi>Edward,</hi> whom we speake off, being deceased, his brother <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>Glocester,</hi> by wicked practises, and vnlawfull meanes, vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the crowne of <hi>England,</hi> defrauding his Nephewes of their inheritance. And as the meane of his vsurping of such a state was strange and cruell, so was the manner of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour in it much more.</p>
            <p>The state of poore <hi>England</hi> was so miserable, that he sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped well, that went cleere with the losse of his goods, offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and fees.</p>
            <p>Many great personages of noble houses, to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues against such a tempest, fled vnto <hi>France.</hi> The noblest, amongst them, was the Earle of <hi>Richmond:</hi> who hauing so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourned a while in <hi>Britanie,</hi> finallie determined to recouer with his goods and possessions the libertie of his country. This new <hi>Thrasybulus,</hi> wāted neither partakers nor friends: for king <hi>Charles</hi> the eight gaue him aide, wherewith hee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21569:10"/>entered into <hi>England,</hi> and there giuing battell with happie successe: he obteined in recompence of his prowesse, the the state and crowne, which hath remained euer since vpon the heads of his posteritie vnto this day. I would not stand so long vppon the commendation of the courtesie of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishmen, if in our time, that is say, within three-score yeares it had not brought foorth so good and euident ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects to our behoofe, as it might argue a blockishnesse in vs to be ignorant of it, and a lewdnesse not to acknowledge it. The realme of <hi>France</hi> neuer receiued so great a blowe since the battell of <hi>Poytiers;</hi> as it did at the ouerthrowe of <hi>Pauie:</hi> where king <hi>Francis</hi> was taken prisoner.</p>
            <p>The Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> being yet a young Prince, and broi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with ambition after so faire victorie, entred into won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull hopes, and in manner assured himselfe, that within few yeares the Monarchie of all <hi>Europe</hi> shoulde bee the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of his <hi>Plus oultre,</hi> that is yet further. And in deede there was great likelihood, that (the forces of <hi>France</hi> being so ouermastered) hee might haue seene, if not in all,<note place="margin">See the histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of du Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay.</note> yet at least in part, the accomplishment of his desires: if God looking vpon our countrie with his pitifull eye, had not touched the heart of <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight king of <hi>England,</hi> to slay the course of the Emperor, pursuing with full sailes the steppes of his victorie (An act so much the more to be wondered at, as that king <hi>Henrie</hi> had not any other cause to do it, than onely his owne princelie disposition, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with his mind was so kindled, that hee thought more for his honour, to releeue his neighbour that was distressed, than to be a partner with the conqueror of the booty and spoile of him) so as, that it may well be said, that king <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> the eight, next after God, was our deliuerer, and that the Lyon hath plucked vs out of the Eagles clawes. And we must not thinke, that in this behalfe he sought his own profite, or peculiar safetie. For as touching the profite, besides that the euent shewed to bee otherwise, the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station that hee made by his king at armes in defying the Emperor, doth sufficiently shew, that the only mark which he aimed at,<note place="margin">Theocritus in the praise of Ptolomie.</note> was honour and royal behauiour: wherby as <hi>Theocritus</hi> affirmed, the great personages of old time haue
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21569:10"/>purchased to thēselues the title of <hi>Heroes.</hi> And as touching safetie, the Emperor being then greatly affectioned to his vncle king <hi>Henrie,</hi> was in treatie, for the greater confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and assurance of friendship, of a marriage betweene himselfe, and the Ladie <hi>Marie,</hi> king <hi>Henries</hi> eldest daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Moreouer, the Emperor could not haue seised vppon the kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> without to bee a partaker of it with the Englishmen, for the olde pretence or title that they make of the countries of <hi>Guyan,</hi> and <hi>Normandie:</hi> So that all things being well accounted, the Englishmen had no cause to be affraid of the Emperor.</p>
            <p>This matter deserued a longer discourse: but I labour to be briefe, that I may speake of <hi>Edward</hi> the sixt, the sonne of king <hi>Henrie.</hi> This prince was so aboundantly indewed with vertue, &amp; the feare of God, that he may iustly be called the <hi>Iosias</hi> of the newe Testament, and the <hi>Phoenix</hi> of Christian princes. But leauing aside his rare vertues, wherof the most eloquent, cannot speake but too ouer briefly: I will touch alonely that which concerned our nyest matter.</p>
            <p>This Prince by the councel of the late duke of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland,</hi> did beare so sound and sincere good will vnto our king, <hi>Henrie</hi> the second, that if God had prolonged his life, there had gone a linke of allyance betweene these two kings, and <hi>Moris</hi> duke of <hi>Saxon.</hi> So that there is great likelihood, that an allyance made betweene three so migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie princes, would euen then haue brought the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> to the same point, which he tooke afterward: that is to wit, to withdraw himselfe in <hi>Castile,</hi> into the Abbie of saint <hi>Iust.</hi> I speake not of the kindnesse that hee shewed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the poore Frenchmen that were driuen to seeke suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, on a time when the profession of Christianitie was no other thing in <hi>France,</hi> then to giue themselues ouer to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent death: and not onelie we, but almost al nations in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> were beholding to England, in that behalfe, forasmuch as their exile was relieued by the helpe and comfort of that most holie and happie <hi>Edward.</hi> Happie (say I) as much in his respect, as that in his sister Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> he hath so persite a pontraiture of his most Christian, &amp; heroicall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. Which is the cause, that all they, that in our <hi>Europe</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21569:11"/>are indewed with a sound iudgement, are desirous aboue all wordly things, either to be subiect vnto such a Prince, or to liue vnder the subiection of a Prince that resembleth her. But I haue not taken in hande to sounde foorth the praises of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> because I am not able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse her rare vertues according as they deserue: and if I woulde go about to lay them forth particularly, I shoulde neuer haue done. Therefore taking a shortenway, I will say onely, that she hath made shew and proofe of her good will towards <hi>France,</hi> as often as the state of our affaires haue offered occasion vnto her most gratious maiestie. and specially, she hath shewed her selfe affectioned to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue peace with vs, (being brought thereunto) as well by her owne cleare insight, as by the well aduised and sage counsell of the most vertuous and excellent Lords, Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Cecill,</hi> yet at this day, Lord Treasurer of <hi>England,</hi> and Sir <hi>Nicholas Bacon,</hi> of good memorie, sometime Lord Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of her Maiesties great Seale: Men indewed with so high and eminent wisedome, and happily qualified with all kinde of vertue, that they may well be numbred among the most eloquent, which can duely sound out their prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to the posteritie. For my part, I thanke our most merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God, which hath so well matched good fortune with so great vertue, in those two English <hi>Nestors,</hi> as that may be seene in them,<note place="margin">Callimachus in Hymno Ionis.</note> the accomplishmēt of the prayer so much solemnized by <hi>Callimachus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Well be to thee father, again well be to thee, Giue vertue and riches then,</l>
               <l>For prosperitie without vertue cannot aduance men,</l>
               <l>Neither vertue without riches: Giue both vertue, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritie then.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21569:11"/>
            <p> Now remaineth to speake of a like vtterance of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship toward vs: howbeit in a verie vnlike case. <hi>France</hi> hath not in it a greater ornament than the cittie of <hi>Paris,</hi> nor the cittie of <hi>Paris</hi> a greater ornament then the exercise of learning, which hath continued there, since the time of <hi>Charlemaine:</hi> that is to say, since the yeare of our Lord. 792. vnto this day: with such estimation, that in the time of our fathers, to haue studied at <hi>Paris,</hi> or to be greatly aduanced in the knowledge of learning, were diuers speeches signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the selfe same thing. Now if this bee a great benefite (as indeede it cannot bee denied, vnlesse it bee of a man of smal iudgement) we cannot confesse to haue the same of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other than of English men, except we will (in depriuing them of the praise that is due vnto them) depriue and rob our selues wilfully, of the reputation of men that loue truth and vpright dealing. For <hi>Charlemaine</hi> was induced to that happie enterprise, by the counsel of <hi>Flaccus Albinus</hi> an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish man (proceeding from an <hi>Italian</hi> stirpe) the which was assisted by two Scots: the one named <hi>Iohn Malrosius,</hi> the other called <hi>Claudius Clemens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now like as euill counsel, by Gods iust iudgement doth redound ordinarily to the hurt of him that giueth it: so contrariwise, the author of good and holy counsell is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, hee that first tasted of the fruites thereof. Euen so the Englishmen haue reaped the fruites of the good, and wholsome counsell of <hi>Albine</hi> and his fellowes: in so much as that the Vniuersitie of <hi>Oxford</hi> is an impe of the same of <hi>Paris.</hi> But because we see, that men are so much more incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to things whereunto they are drawne by the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that which touched them most neerely: I wil say, that the wellfare of <hi>England</hi> toucheth vs so nigh, and ours them, that if the one of both these nations bee beaten downe by the stranger, the other may well make her rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning, that shee shall not inioy any great rest. It is well knowne, that assoone as <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> had taken footing with the <hi>Romane</hi> power in <hi>France,</hi> hee thought not to haue well played his part, vntill he had passed into <hi>Britaine,</hi> to make a broile there. The historie writers haue so clarified this point, that it were superfluitie of speach to proceede anie
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21569:12"/>farther in the discourse thereof. I woulde faine nowe, that some one of these iolly fellowes, our courtiers, which are so affectioned, &amp; make so great a matter of the allyance with <hi>Spaine,</hi> would shew me the like reasons and ground of their opinion. I am verie well assured that they will not trouble themselues to prooue any natural affinitie betweene <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> vnlesse they ransacke vp from the Arke of <hi>Noe:</hi> or else that they will make anie account of that which the Poets report, concerning the faire, and beautifull <hi>Bebrice.</hi> The which notwithstanding, woulde bee an argument so weake, as euill to purpose, as they know that are skilfull in the knowledg of antiquities, &amp; specially of poetical fables.</p>
            <p>Now being entred into this matter, it shal not be imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to speake of the originall of the Spaniards that are at this day. For we see that the waters which come from a spring where Brimstone is, do alwayes sent the Brimstone: so is it commonly seene, that men do carry printed in their manners and behauiour, the vertuous or vitious qualities, of their ancestors. Thus hauing knowledge of the original, and issue of the Spaniards, that wil be vnto vs a good path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to the discourse following. About the yeare of Christ. 717. <hi>Iulian</hi> Earle of <hi>Biscay</hi> being greatly greeued, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to reuenge himselfe of the outrage by him receiued at the hands of <hi>Roderike,</hi> K. of the <hi>Gothes,</hi> which had deflowred his daughter, called and drew the <hi>Moores</hi> to his aid, vnder the leading of <hi>Muza Miramamolin</hi> their King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋnder this p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>text</hi> (so sure a thing is it to drawe forraine forces into a countrie) the <hi>Moores</hi> made themselues ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of all <hi>Spaine,</hi> sauing <hi>Biscay</hi> and <hi>Austerland:</hi> For after their captaines had parted the countrie which they had conquered, they became so manie little kings in <hi>Spaine.</hi> Since the Sarazins intermingled themselues yet further: insomuch, that if we will take vp the matters further off: that is to wit, from the time of <hi>Caesar,</hi> wee shal, finde that without speaking of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> who haue comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded most of all <hi>Europe,</hi> the Gothes, the Vandales, the Moores and the Sarasines, haue beene the Lawgiuers to <hi>Spaine.</hi> Therefore, if of good right, the Gothes &amp; Vandales are accounted cruel, the Moores faithlesse &amp; reuengeful, &amp;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21569:12"/>the Sarasins proud, &amp; ful of villanie in their conuersations.</p>
            <p>I pray you, what humanitie, what faith, what gentlenes, what mildenesse and ciuilitie thinke wee to find in that son of barbarousnesse? But, to the intent it be not taught, that I will rest vpon bare presumptions, rather then vpon sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiall proofes and arguments: I am contented that this article shall bee cleared by conferring their manners with ours, that is to say, their vices with our vertues, and their villaqueries or knaueries, with our courtesies. To be short, this comparison is such, that if any Rhethorician would bestow his eloquence, making a long and liuelie countermatch, he could not choose in the whole world a subiect more answerable to his purpose, than the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of our cōditions with the cōditions of this Marranish nation of Spaniards. And to the end it be not thought, that I speak feinedly, for an entry into the deuise of their fairest colour, I will bring them foorth one witnesse which shall make them blush for shame: notwithstanding that they be so shamelesse, that they wil not willingly blush. Whē I shuld onely say, that the witnesse which I intend to bring against them, is a Senator of <hi>Ʋenice,</hi> yet shoulde I haue sufficientlie qualified it, to purchase him credit among al men of discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and setled iudgement. But I will say yet further, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he is an ancient Senator: yea, and so trained vp in the affaires of this world, that the conforming of men to his imitation, is nothing else at this day among the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, than to be the verie direct way to attaine immortall renowne, by a most sage and wise ordering of matters of state: to be short, it is that excellent and renowmed perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, <hi>Andrew Gritte,</hi> who in discoursing before the Senate of <hi>Venice,</hi> vpon the honorable behauiour of this good Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish race: behold the faire testimonie which he rendereth of their good disposition and nature. The Spanish nation (saith he) is vnfaithfull, ouerrauenous, and vnsatiablest of all other nations. And where is, I pray you, the place of the worlde,<note place="margin">Guychardin in Lib. 16.</note> where these infamous Harpyes haue set their feete, which is not defiled with the footsteps of their abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable vices?</p>
            <p>And forasmuch as in the proofe of a matter, the witnes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21569:13"/>of one alone, is of no great weight. I will produce yet an other witnesse: that is to wit, <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>Guichiardine,</hi> Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographer:<note place="margin">Guychardin in Lib. 16.</note> a man so sufficient, that the verie reckoning vp of his good gifts and perfections, would require and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue a whole historie.</p>
            <p>Lo here the record which he yeeldeth to the Spanish di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposition, and loyaltie: The Spanish nation (saith hee, in giuing his iudgement of those reuerend fathers) are coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and deceitfull (and where they be at libertie, and haue meanes to discouer themselues in their kind as they be) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding outrageous, proud and insolent. <hi>Geryon</hi> king of <hi>Spaine</hi> (if we may beleeue the fables of Poets) had three bodies: and although this bee poeticall deuise, yet will it seeme the lesse strange, by him which shall consider the Spaniards nature throughly: wherein may be seene incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated together, a craftie Foxe, a rauenous Woolfe, and a wounding Tygre. And let this be said, in respect of those of that nation, which are least intollerable: for whosoeuer looketh thoroughly into the deepest degree of them: that is to say, into the wickedder and abhominabler sort, then the common be, he shal finde in euerie of them the Cube: yea many times the Sursolide of this ternarie mōster. They shall be found (I say) a filthy and loathsome swine, a thee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uish Howlet, and a bragging Peacocke. As for the fulnesse of their perfection, there shall be found in them a legion of diuels: practising howe to lie, to intrappe, and to deceiue the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Briareus</hi> (as <hi>Homer</hi> saith) had an hundred hands:<note place="margin">Homers Iliads. <hi>ae.</hi>
               </note> who will beleeue that the Spanyard hath any lesse, when it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to catching and snatching. Let him but receiue for a day or two, some Dom diego into his house, &amp; if he change not of aduise, I am contented to grant and confesse, that the Spaniard hath changed his condition: I say, if robberie and theeuerie ought to bee accounted, rather a custome, than naturall in that nation. And if anie man doubt of their sufficiencie in that behalfe: the state of the Low countries will make it so manifest, that he will of his owne accord confesse, that the Bohemians, and Aegyptians, are but small prentises to the Spaniards, in taking and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriating
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21569:13"/>other mens goods to themselues. And surely, he should do them great wrong which should thinke that time hath not made them more cunning in their craft, spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this latter yeares, wherein the most part of these lustie gallants haue serued their prentiship vnder <hi>Don Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinando</hi> of <hi>Toledo,</hi> who was so great and principall a crafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master in that facultie, that to compare to him an <hi>Antoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> or a <hi>Verres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virgillin his first Aeglog.</note> were a falling into the errour of the sheep-heard <hi>Tytirus,</hi> by comparing of small thinges, to things o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uergreat. But it seemeth to be a thing resonable, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale the imperfections of that great Captaine, in conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the excellent partes that are in him.</p>
            <p>For by report of his disciples and footement, he is secret, well aduised, and of great forecast. As touching his tacitur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, I doubt not a whit, but that hee is very secret. And likewise there is nothing in his dooings, speciallie in his owne particular and familiar, which may not by him, and his, with more honestie be concealed, than vttered.</p>
            <p>As concerning his great wisedome, and cleare insight in matters: he hath giuen such a proofe thereof, in his orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the affaires of <hi>Flanders:</hi> that if the sunne should as often want his light in the skie, as his good wit wanted in his head, during that time: we might well conclude, that we were at the last instant of the day, that shall make an end to the thinges of this world. At the least, it is notoriously knowen, that he was so farre destitute of sense, that he was not able to hide, not onely the pilferies &amp; robberies which he had committed vpon the poore people, (for that thing was too much knowen) but his trayterous stealing which he hath committed, euen of his masters treasure. I knowe very well, that his owne creatures, disguising and turning his deedes, say that he is remayned a successor. But setting aside this colour of Castilian rethoricke: I will say flatly, that our french tongue is so barraine, that it hath not any other termes fit ynough to specifie the goodly gouernment of the Duke of <hi>Alua,</hi> but onely theeuery and robberie of the common treasure. And therefore if he imploy his pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie now a dayes as well in playing vpon the lute in <hi>Spaine,</hi> as he did in playing vpon the harpe in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21569:14"/>
            <p> King <hi>Philip</hi> hath good cause to sende his <hi>Seuerino</hi> into <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> againe: but howsoeuer the case stand, the king his master hath restrayned his couetousnesse: howbeit not with ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, hauing peraduenture respect to the order of the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fleece, the which, I dare well say, he beareth to no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end, than because he hath first slaine, and afterwardes deuoured the innocent sheepe of the good shepheard.</p>
            <p>For we must not thinke, that he, and the residue of the rakehell Spaniardes, haue any more spared the bloud, than the purses, of the poore people of the Lowe Countries. And why should they not, sith they had commandement so to do. And their Prince was displeased at nothing so much, as that they had not handled them yet more rigorously?</p>
            <p>O that thou new <hi>Pharao,</hi> mightest by thy dolefull death, soone make an ende of the sorrowful sighes of so many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solate persons!</p>
            <p>And if any man thinke, that the difference of Religion, was the very cause of the venemous and spitefull rancour of the Spaniards against the people of the low countries: he showes himselfe to be ignorant, as well of their nature, as of their state and affaires. It is about a hundred yeares ago that they discouered a new world, by the leading of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stopher Columbe,</hi> who (in mine opinion) would neuer haue enterprised that voyage, if hee had thought, that the men whom he led thether, should like folke bewitched with the slaber sauces of <hi>Circe,</hi> haue foorthwith beene transformed into Lyons, Panthers, Tygres, and such other wilde beasts. The <hi>Indians</hi> and <hi>Americans,</hi> being sillie soules, vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and barbarous, might lightly haue beene (by an honest conuersation and holy teaching) won vnto Christ, as appeareth by the Frenchmen, who afterwarde, no lesse wisely than fortunately went that way to worke. But a man may well say, according to the truth, that the new worlde, of <hi>India</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> was not so much vnknowen to the former ages past, as the outragious and newe deuised cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties, which these diuels incarnate, that came out of <hi>Spaine</hi> haue practised there. O Turkes, O Scithians, O Tartarians, reioyce ye all as now: sith that there is to be founde at this day a Nation in Christendome, which by their vnhappie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21569:14"/>cursed behauiour, doo go about to burie the hatred that men beare to your barbarous cruelties. But I tarrie too long vpon so tragical a matter, the which notwithstanding I do with so great griefe, as vpon iust cause.</p>
            <p>Therefore leauing that matter, which were able to make euen <hi>Democritus</hi> to weepe: let vs speake of two pointes, which are such, that whosoeuer heareth them and conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them throughly, must be of a more melancholicke humour, and dumpish disposition than euer was <hi>Heracli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> if he aan forbeare laughing. The matter concerneth their ciuilitie, and modestie. As touching the first, if any man haue had the happe neuer to haue beene in companie of the Spaniardes, and yet would faine be truely informed of their Gothish ciuilitie, hee could not see a more liuely protraiture, nor a more apparant draught thereof, drawen by the hande of any more happie <hi>Appelles,</hi> than is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of whores, which <hi>Terence</hi> maketh in his Comedie intituled <hi>Eunuch,</hi> in these wordes.</p>
            <q>Quae dum foris sunt, nihil videtur mundius, nec magis compositum quicquam, nec magis elegans.</q>
            <p>And a little after he addeth:</p>
            <q>Harum videre est ingluuiem, sordes, inopiam, quàm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honestae solae sint domi, atque auidae cibi: quo pacto ex iure hesterno panem atrum vorent.</q>
            <p>That is to say, While they be abroade nothing seemeth more neate, nothing more trimme, neyther more fine. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereunto a little farther: It is a worlde to see them at home, how rauenous, howe sluttish, how nigardly, and how vnwomanly they be alone by themselues, greedie at their meate, and cramming themselues with browne bread and pottage of a day old and more.</p>
            <p>I would say more, if that it could be doone without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of the tender and most delicate stomackes. Wee haue here set foorth the Spaniardes in sport, as good Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, that is to saye, to make them to serue vs for laughing stockes at their cost. And who is the man (I pray you) so melancholicke, that could with-holde himselfe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21569:15"/>from laughing, seeing a porter, a cobler, and a carman, to play the Caualiero: or a Caualiero of <hi>Spaine,</hi> walking in the fieldes, and carrying the remnant of his dinner in his by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacke: and doing a thousande such other villanies, of the which the porters, coblers, and carremen of this countrie would be sorrie to haue thought vpon.</p>
            <p>The Mathematikes teach, that in the operations of Alge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar, the most equall is oftentimes reduced to the most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall.</p>
            <p>The speeches of the Spaniardes, doo somewhat resemble this diuine Algebricall misterie, if you consider what, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily this great and stately title of rich Caualiero, that may spende ten thousand ducats a yeare, doo commonly import (being taken a right, and at the very true rate and value) an vnthrift, a rascall, and a vagabonde beggar, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing not scarce thirtie maluedies in his purse, wherwith to haue mended his sockes. In so much that it may well bee said to these Magnifical <hi>Don Diegos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch in the life of Phocion.</note> as a certaine great man of <hi>Athens</hi> said sometimes to certaine Orators, Your words (saide he) be like to the Cypresse, which beeing great and high, do neuerthelesse beare no fruite.</p>
            <p>To make it short, whosoeuer will see the liuely protray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of an Attalus, a Suffenus, or a Thraso, without trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling himselfe too much in ouerturning the leaues of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, Catullus,</hi> or <hi>Terence:</hi> let him but beholde the grim vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, and stately speech of a Spaniard. And although these <hi>Sarrasins</hi> race be of such qualities as I haue saide, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding they haue (with the shot of their Pistolets) so well dazeled the eyes of some of our Courtiers, that they be not ashamed to mainteine, that wee are greatly behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to these honest creatures.</p>
            <p>For my part (I confesse) I haue not so fine a wit as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the foundation of this obligation, vnlesse they take it in the samesense that <hi>Antiochus</hi> ment,<note place="margin">Cicero in his oration for Deiotarus.</note> when he said, he was greatly beholding to the <hi>Romaines,</hi> the which hauing short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and abridged him of his authoritie &amp; power, had eased him of a great and heauie burthen. Euen so are we behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Spaniardes, for easing vs of the tedious toyles, which the gouernmēts of the States of <hi>Flanders, Naples,</hi> and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21569:15"/>
               <hi>Millaine,</hi> might haue brought vnto vs. And to speake yet farther of their good will towardes vs: Is it not a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde of this heartie loue and Spanish fauour,<note place="margin">Looke Froy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sard.</note> the which they vsed in times past vpō our ancesters (according to their cruell nature) to wit, that when they had wonne the battell vpon vs, they killed all the prisoners which they had taken euen when the heate of their bloud &amp; courage was alaid, as <hi>Froysarde</hi> witnesseth? Would a man haue a more euident in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation than this, of the foresaid testimonie which we alleaged out of <hi>Guychardine,</hi> saying that this Nation is too too outragious, whē she hath found aduantage to discouer her selfe, such as she is (that is to say) to put off the vizard of her hypocrisie? Also another token and witnesse of their humanitie towards vs, may well be the murthering of our men contrarie to their faith &amp; promise giuen in the land of <hi>Florida,</hi> about twentie yeares ago. I had almost forgotten to alleage one notable and speciall deede of their cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie towardes vs, namely their imprisoning of <hi>Francis</hi> our King, of the which hee himselfe did complaine, so much the more surely (as <hi>Guychardine</hi> reporteth) as the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the English courtesie towardes king <hi>Iohn,</hi> was the more deepely ingrauen in his minde. What recorde of friendshippe is it that the Spaniardes may alleage vnto vs, shall it not bee the succour which they gaue vs, by <hi>Henrie</hi> king of <hi>Castile,</hi> in the time of Kinge <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth,<note place="margin">Looke Froy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sard.</note> by helpe whereof he gate the vpper hand of the Earle of <hi>Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooke</hi> before <hi>Rochell?</hi> As if the same king <hi>Henrie</hi> himselfe, had not, reaped the chiefe fruite of that victorie. Or as though his assisting vs in that wise, was not the principall bulwarke of his owne estate.</p>
            <p>But nowe, as the Englishmen are answerable vnto vs in a great number of thinges, as I haue rehearsed before: so haue they tasted of this miserie as well as we: namely, that they haue had to their cost experience of the ouer dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous friendshippe of the Spaniardes. For <hi>Philip</hi> king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and at that time king of <hi>Englande</hi> also, beeing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to haue gotten <hi>Callis</hi> into his owne possession, occasioned vs Frenchmen, to doo with the Lyons pawe, that which the Spaniards were minded to do by the Foxes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21569:16"/>tooth. Otherwise the Frenchmen would hardly haue resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them to so dangerous and doubtfull an enterprise as the siege of <hi>Callis</hi> was.</p>
            <p>To make it short, it may well be said, that that Nation of all other in the world, is most affectioned towardes the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale of <hi>France,</hi> that resembled least the Spanish Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The which thing I conclude so much the more boldly, because I am well assured, that no man will trouble himself to prooue that they haue helped or furthered vs, either in the knowledge of good learning, or in the ordering of our manners. For what light of good learning is to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for at the hands of that nation, which during this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie age hath scarce brought forth siue or sixe learned men? This is the cause in mine opinion, why the Spaniardes (as great trauellers as they be) durst neuer passe so farre,<note place="margin">Pindarus ode x. Pith.</note> as to the <hi>Hiperboreans,</hi> for feare (as it is to be thought) least they retayning still their old custome of offering vp of Asses in sacrifice, might haue sacrificed them. As touching the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of our manners, we may well say, that as the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher <hi>Polianus</hi> (by dealing too much with the dreaming do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of <hi>Epicurus</hi>) forgat all skill that he had of Geometry,<note place="margin">Cicero in Lucullo.</note> so we by the familiaritie of the Spaniards, haue almost for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the vertues which were most familiar vnto vs, to wit, courtesie and humanitie.</p>
            <p>And to what purpose (I pray you) should beare any great good affection to vs that Nation which should take so smal harme by our ouerthrow: or rather which hath alwaies and specially for this last hundred yeres groūded hir own great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vpon our abatement. I cut off this discourse of purpose to touch another point of greater importance: namely the meanes which either of the Nations haue to helpe or to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy vs withall. I will speake therefore at first of that which concerneth trafficke, and afterwarde of such as touch Martiall actes. All those which knowe both <hi>Englande</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> will grant vnto mee, that <hi>Englande</hi> is much more peopled than <hi>Spaine.</hi> I speake not proportion for propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but euen in the whole: notwithstanding that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande</hi> be farre lesse in quantitie of lande: which thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth of nothing else, than of the temperature of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21569:16"/>place. For although <hi>Fraunce</hi> bee one of the temperatest countries that are knowen: yet neuerthelesse <hi>Caesar</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereof, sayeth expressely of Englande, <hi>Loca sunt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratiora quàm in Gallia:</hi> The places are more temperate then in <hi>France.</hi> This abundance of people,<note place="margin">Pindarus ode 1. Olimp.</note> is a sure argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the fruitefulnesse of the soyle. <hi>Pindarus</hi> in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine place tearmeth <hi>Cicilie</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to say, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant of sheepe. And expounding himselfe in an other place, he nameth it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to say, fat or fruitefull.<note place="margin">Pind. Od. 1. Nem.</note> If this argument of that so learned a Poet be well couched, we may well thereupon conclude the fruitefulnesse of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande,</hi> by the great abundance not only of sheepe, but also generally of all cattell which be in it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cicero in Lucullo.</note>It may be that here some man will obiect the saying of <hi>Cicero</hi> in his Oration intituled, <hi>De Aruspicum responsis.</hi> That is the answere of the birdspellers, for behold how he spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, euen in these wordes:</p>
            <q>Quam volumus, licèt ipsi nos amemus: tamen nec nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero Hispanos, nec robore Gallos, nec calliditate Poenos, nec artibus Graecos, nec denique hoc ipso huius gentis ac ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raenatiuo sensu Italos ipsos ac Latinos, sed pictate ac religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne omnes gentes ac nationes superauin us.</q>
            <p>Stande we as much as we list in our owne conceites, yet neyther in number excell we the Spaniards, nor in strength the Galles, nor in pollicie the <hi>Poenians</hi> or <hi>Cartheginians,</hi> nor in sciences the Grecians, nor finally in sharpenesse of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall wit, the Italians and Latines, beeing of this selfe same countrie, and lande that we be: only in godlinesse and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, haue we outgone all countries and all nations.</p>
            <p>But in this place it is easie to iudge, that in this saying <hi>Cicero</hi> was led rather by his eares, than by his eyes, as well as he was in his former saying, speaking of Astrologers. And that in this discourse, it pleased him to play the part of an other <hi>Mirmecides</hi> in making a great case of a smal mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But what neede we to stande so much vpon this point,<note place="margin">Plinius lib. 7. cap. 21.</note> seeing that the trafick which we haue with both those coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries can easily dispatch that doubt.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21569:17"/>
            <p> We receiue out of <hi>Englande,</hi> Wooll, Tinne, Fish, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other thinges, in great abundance: and in exchange thereof we furnish them with wine, Salt, woade, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse other thinges: by reason whereof it commeth to passe, that <hi>Rochell, Burdeaux,</hi> and generally all the sea costes of <hi>Normandie, Britaine</hi> and <hi>Gwyen,</hi> are brought to great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse, by ceasing the traficke with the Englishmen.</p>
            <p>Out of <hi>Spaine</hi> (I confesse) we drawe verie good horses of seruice, howbeit, that is but by stealth. And in granting this point (notwithstanding that it go against my heart to do it) I am driuen to confesse the slothfulnes of vs French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. For if we would keepe the like races of horses, and mares, as are to be seene in <hi>Lauedan,</hi> our trade with the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niardes might seeme to proceede of pure charitie, because we should relieue them without receiuing any helpe or suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour at their handes. For the marchandice of some perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med gloues, and such other small baggages, deserueth not to come in any account. And forasmuch as concerne thē, they by reason of the drinesse &amp; barrennesse of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, be driuen to borrow of vs, the thing most needfull for mans life, to wit, corne. As for wine they haue sufficient of their owne. Now remaineth the trade or wooll, &amp; of cloth, both woollen and linnen, which amounteth not to the third part of that which our marchants receiue out of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. And it will not seiue their turne to say, that they may leauie great quantities of corne, from the places which they keepe in <hi>Italy,</hi> as out of <hi>Naples, Cicilie</hi> and <hi>Millaine:</hi> for they that flourish the matter with that faire face, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider not, that so to do, were but a stripping of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and cloth Saint <hi>Paule. Cicilie</hi> is fruitefull, I graunt it, but <hi>Malta</hi> and the <hi>Goze,</hi> must be sustained by that fruiteful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, vnlesse they intende to make them selues a pray to the Turkes, by leauing those places vnvictualed. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, a good part of the fruites of <hi>Cicilie</hi> are imployed in the mayntenance of <hi>Italie.</hi> And as in respect of <hi>Millaine</hi> and <hi>Lombardie,</hi> the carriage is difficult from thence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Spayne,</hi> that they can by no meanes helpe themselues with the fruites thereof, but that the sauce will stande them in more than the fish is woorth.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21569:17"/>
            <p> As for <hi>Naples, Pouil,</hi> and <hi>Calabrie,</hi> for as much as the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse of them is not verie great, the Spaniard can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the lesse succour of them. The like may bee saide in respect of the Low-countries. Some man perchance will thinke it strange, that I should stand so much vppon the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfulnesse of <hi>Spaine,</hi> seing that the great meanes which that nation hath to succour vs with all, are more than suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to counteruaile that default. Heere must I needes bring to passe the <hi>Quolibet,</hi> which the Romane Iudges were wont to vse, when they found themselues in perplexitie for the deciding of some matter of importance: that is to wit, <hi>Non liquet,</hi> It appeareth not so: But this perplexitie of mine, is so much the lesse, because it may easily be resolued by comparing the helpes and meanes of <hi>England,</hi> with the helpes of <hi>Spaine.</hi> If we measure these helps and meanes, by the number of souldiers that can set foorth the one or the other of those nations: the experience, that is to say, the verie historie pleadeth openly for the Englishmen. And for proofe hereof, <hi>Comynes</hi> witnesseth, that the fore mentioned king <hi>Edward,</hi> sent to the succour of the Duke of <hi>Burgoine,</hi> fifteene hundred horsemen well mounted, for the most part vppon barbed horses, richly furnished: and also fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene thousand archers on horsebacke.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Guychardine Lib. 12.</note>In our time king <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, at his first comming downe into <hi>Picardie</hi> to ioyne with the Emperor <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> (the first of that name) at the siege of <hi>Terwane,</hi> brought with him fiue thousand horsemen, and aboue fortie thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand footemen, of whom fiue and twentie thousand were Englishmen, and fifteene thousand were Lance knights: What can bee said of the like in the behalfe of the Spanish nation? The Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> and his sonne king <hi>Philip,</hi> are the princes that haue most absolutely commanded in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and yet for all that, neither of them both could euer leuie a greater power of men of warre, than eight thousand naturall Spaniards, and yet the most of them were foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. For as concerning the horsemen, the Spaniard may be compared vnto a sworde fish, who hath a good blade, and cannot helpe himselfe with it. The like may well bee said, that the Spaniards haue verie good horses, but they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21569:18"/>serue them with it, more to traffike with their friends, than to fight with their enimies, to withstand them. But because that the remembrance of late things may serue very much to discourse this doubt, I will set downe a record so cleere &amp; euident, that whosoeuer will take vpon him to aduance the forces of the Spaniards, shal haue no better foundation to ground himselfe vpon, than either an ouerlight beliefe, or else an head-strong wilfulnesse. During the reigne of K. <hi>Francis</hi> the second, at what time the great men of <hi>France</hi> were in verie euil plight among themselues. K. <hi>Philip</hi> wrote a letter to the K. which was read before his priuy counsell. I cannot wel tel in what language it was written, but surely the contents thereof sauored much of the Spanish phrase: for hee protested, that if any remoouing came againe in <hi>France,</hi> hee woulde aide the King his brother with an armie of fiftie thousand men. A while after, both the time and occasion offered themselues verie well, for him to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that which he had so solemnly protested: for <hi>France</hi> was beaten downe with the storme of ciuill warre. And although our miseries did cause well-neere as manie fountaines of teares, as there be townes in <hi>France.</hi> So that they ministred occasion vnto King <hi>Philip</hi> to reioyce that hee had so fit an occasion to accomplish his promise. Let vs see therefore howe hee discharged himselfe thereof. He was required to sende succour to the king his brother, who was about to stablish againe the Romish religion in her former state. Nowe to the intent hee might not seeme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, in good will and friendship towards his brother, hee gathered certaine troopes of those vertuous and religious persons, which liue in the straights of the mountaines <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renees,</hi> by taking the gold without vewing it, and the siluer without telling it: and yet were not they to the number of fiftie thousand, as he had promised, but onely vnto two thousand: so that it was easie to iudge vnto all Arithmeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, that this good prince, when hee made this foresaide protestation, hee reckened his helpes and meanes by the rule of false position. As touching the behauiour of these braue and valiant souldiers, if a man considered them throughly, they represented I cannot tell what image, of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21569:18"/>the olde forworne age of the world,<note place="margin">Thucidides, lib primo.</note> during the which (as witnessed <hi>Thucidides</hi>) robbing and stealing was no shame. The contemplation of these goodly qualities made the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Catholikes so much the more lorie for the losse of these honest men: for hauing incamped them vppon the banke of the riuer of <hi>Tard,</hi> those <hi>Amazones</hi> of <hi>Mountauban,</hi> issuing out diuers times vppon them, slewe a great sort of them without confession and penance for any other sinne, than onely of that, which is termed temeritie and ouersight of warre. But nowe for as much as in making comparison diuers things one to another,<note place="margin">Aristot. lib. quinto Ethie.</note> the proportion of Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie beareth far greater sway than the proportion of Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metike: that man should not transgresse much the bounds of reason, which should take vpon him to iudge of these two nations (in matters of warre) rather by the valor and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines, than by the number, for oftentimes a smal number of men do ouermaster a great armie, and treade them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foote. I am exceeding sorie, that I cannot produce bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter presidents of the English prowesse, than the great &amp; sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular victories which they haue gotten vpon vs: howbeit that our valiant ancesters in those battels, wanted nothing lesse then corage and good will. The Englishmen can glorie of nothing more, than that they ouercame such enimies, as were most valiant: in somuch that the Poets &amp; history wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which haue set out their prosperitie, haue not at anie time cōcealed our valiantnes. To be short, the manhood &amp; prowesse of our ancesters, deserued not to be ouercome of any but of such enimies as could skil to ouercome, euen vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory it self: that is to say, the fury &amp; outrage, which is wont to accompany the victorious armes. Let the <hi>Carthaginenses</hi> boast as much as they list of their successe of <hi>Cannas:</hi> for yet if they go about to prefer it, before the battel of <hi>Cressie,</hi> they shal but shew thē, either too much affectioned to thēselues, or else ouer smally skilled in the knowledge of the historie: whereout we may gather, that in the said renowned battell (which was fought in the yeere 1346. there were slaine on our side, aleuen princes, fourscore barons, a thousād &amp; two hundred housemen, &amp; more then thirty thousand footmē. Also the battel of <hi>Poytiers</hi> (wherof I haue spokē heretofore)
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21569:19"/>yeeldeth the like record, both of the English manhood in getting the victorie, and of their courtesie and mildnesse in knowing how to vse it moderately: the which thing cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth me to speake the more freely of their prowesse and vertue. And to confesse the more plainely, that the small number of fighting men which were on their side, haue made their victories the more renowmed and notable, it were against reason, that in this comparison I shoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Spaniards to furnish me with the like presidents, of their owne prowesse and valiancie: for they be dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of so doing by the rule of right, which saith, that no man is bounde to the performance of thinges that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible.</p>
            <p>Againe, I am afraid I should bee counted a forger of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes and incredible tales, if I should say that the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards are not stout men of warre, vnlesse I had so cleare and euident proofe thereof, that to denie the same were a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full shutting of a mans eyes, least hee shoulde not see the brightnesse of the sunne at high noone. And to the intent to wade deeper into this matter, and to speake of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects by their causes. I say that if nature hath not altered the ordinarie course of her working, the Spaniard cannot in any wise be accounted among the warlike nations.<note place="margin">Aristot. in his vij. booke of matters of state. cap. 7.</note> The nations which dwell in cold countries (as <hi>Aristotle</hi> saith) are indewed with a more hautie and stout courage than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but of wit not so quicke and sharpe: and therefore they loue more their libertie, but are lesse able to wielde the sterne of soueraintie ouer their neighbours. Contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the nations of <hi>Asia</hi> haue a more waking wit, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a baser courage, they yeeld more willingly their necks vnder the yoke of bondage: and therefore he concludeth that the Greeks, as holding the meane betweene extreame heat, and extreame cold, are indifferently partakers of both these complexions. Now, as his proposition is grounded vpon a good consideration, so all men of good vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding will alwaies vphold the same: And I dare well say, that in the applying thereof, the loue of truth gaue place to the loue of his countrie: for the most Northerne part of <hi>Greece,</hi> is of foure and fortie degrees, which is the eleuation
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21569:19"/>of that quarter where <hi>Constantinople</hi> standeth, as also is the eleuation of the mountaine <hi>Pyrenees,</hi> which separate <hi>France</hi> from <hi>Spaine.</hi> Therefore parting the fiue and fortith degree which is the verie bounde of temperatnesse: marking the midst of <hi>France,</hi> wee may well say that our countrie is more temperate than <hi>Greece.</hi> And although <hi>England</hi> bee as much or more Northerly than any part of <hi>France,</hi> yet notwithstā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, because it is enuironed with the Occean on all sides,<note place="margin">Pind. ode 1. Nem.</note> the colde is nothing so excessiue there, as it is in <hi>France,</hi> as <hi>Caesar</hi> hath verie wel noted. And therefore it is easie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that by reason of the situation of the place, the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishmen are both warlike and also wise, that is to say, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly furnished with whatsoeuer is necessarie to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of the ciuill life. For the strength of the bodie is no lesse required in executing,<note place="margin">Cicero in his Oration for M. Marcellus.</note> than the finenesse &amp; liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse of wit is in deuising, as saith very wel the Poet <hi>Pinda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>For the power worketh by operation,</l>
               <l>But the wit with counsell and discretion.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And it wil not serue to say, as <hi>Comines</hi> doth, that the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishmen be verie cholerike, a passion which aboue al others troubleth mens iudgements, specially when they be at the point to resolue thēselues: for that might take place in the time of <hi>Comines,</hi> when Englishmen were not yet so well po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, as they haue bin since, by the knowledge of good learning. But since that by the liberality of K. <hi>Edward</hi> wee haue seene two <hi>Athens</hi> in one <hi>England</hi> onely, (that is to wit, <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford</hi>) it were hard to iudge whether that so mighty a realme, hath bin more plentifull in fruites of the earth, then in fine subtill, and most excellent wits, meet for the managing of matters of state.<note place="margin">Machiauell in his booke of a Prince.</note> It is about three or foure score yeares past, that the Italians made to the Frenchmen, the same reproch, that <hi>Commines</hi> doth to the Englishmen: namely that they could not skill in matters of gouernmēt. But since the time that king <hi>Francis</hi> replenished <hi>France</hi> with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21569:20"/>learned men, by the meanes of the Professors, the which from al parts he caused to come to <hi>Paris:</hi> the Italians should flatter themselues too much, if they thought that in the handling of politike affaires, the Frenchmen should be any whit behind them. And it is therefore that <hi>Peter Rame</hi> (a man whose renowne flieth daylie thorough all the coasts of the worlde) had such a minde to commend in his familiar talke, the great liberality, and other excellent vertues of K. <hi>Edward</hi> and queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that hee neuer thought to haue found so meete a matter, whereon to bestow his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull eloquence, as to discourse the nature and heroicall vertue, whereof he described a true and liuely portrature, in the doings and behauiour of those two princes. But the desire which I haue, with the fit meane which is offered me to shew that the Spaniard is no warlike man, maketh mee to be somewhat shorter in discoursing of the wisedome of the Englishmen. I thinke that the reason which I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged out of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> is sufficient enough to displace the Spaniards out of the roome which hee pretendeth to haue among warlike Nations. Neuerthelesse, if any man had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to referre himselfe to the experience, than to his Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophicall reasons, I haue but too many meanes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to content him, if he be a man, that will admit reason for payment. I say therefore, that before this last hundred yeeres, the Spanish nation was had in no reputation, for feats of armes. And for proofe thereof, I report me to the witnesse of histories: I say more, that since that time, looke howe often the princes of <hi>Spaine</hi> haue grounded the chiefe force of their armies vppon bands of the Spanish nation, so often haue they alwayes receiued some great blowe or ouerthrow. The battel of <hi>Rauenna,</hi> and <hi>Serizoles,</hi> in <hi>Lombar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi> do sufficiently verifie my saying. On the contrarie part, if they had aduantage against vs, as they had at <hi>Pauia,</hi> at saint <hi>Quintins,</hi> and at <hi>Graueling,</hi> they ought to thanke the Almaines and Englishmen for it. Verily, I confesse, that vnder the wise conducting of the Emperour <hi>Charles,</hi> they were brought to a certaine orderly discipline, which they continue, and shall continue so long as it shall please God to vse their seruice, for executing of his rightful vēgeance:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21569:20"/>for it is hee that both' giueth, &amp; taketh vertue, to and from men, and when he listeth, as the Poet <hi>Homer</hi> hath very wel noted saying.<note place="margin">Hom. Iliades.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>God incresed and diminished vertue vnto men,</l>
               <l>As it pleased him, for he surpassed all them.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And although the Spaniards surpasse all other nations of the world in vaine and foolish boasting, when they fall in question of their owne prowesse and valiance: yet do they labor to surmount themselues in this shamelesse bragging, when they come to speake of their wealth and riches. And forasmuch as this is the chiefe foundation of their imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiue greatnesse, I will stande somewhat the longer vppon this point, and I will make it to bee knowne, that if they had the thirde part of the riches which they imagine to haue, they should be three times richer than they bee.<note place="margin">Theophrast. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The Aegyptians reported in their histories, that in the temple of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> there was a piller made of foure Emerauds, contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning euerie of them fourty cubits of length, whereat <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraestus</hi> iested verie pleasantly, and with good reason. Such like accounts are to be found in the histories of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, concerning the Ile of <hi>Zipangrie,</hi> where these good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes would faine make vs to beleeue that flies cary staues pyked on both ends. As touching the treasure of <hi>Perou,</hi> to the intent men might vnderstand, that their reports are set downe by imitation of <hi>Lucians</hi> true tales: they seeme not to haue forgotten any thing vntold, sauing that in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet of king <hi>Atapaliba,</hi> they founde a whole hundred of Diamonds, euery of them as big at least as an Ostriches egge. But setting aside these lies, which cannot be beleeued but of such as beleeue the reall veritie of Metamorphose, or transformation of <hi>Ouid:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs consider, that these riches come not into the king of Spaines coffers, like grasse in a medow, that is to say, without any cost: but contrariwise, that the fetching
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21569:21"/>thereof costeth him very deere. Let vs consider farther, that other nations, and specially the Frenchmen, haue learned the way to <hi>Perou,</hi> who fearing perhaps, least the Spaniards might perish vpon sea by being ouerladen, do diuers times of pure charitie and good will, yeeld them so much seruice, as to take some part of their burthen into their ships (yea so gratious and friendly be our Frenchmen) that they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the Spaniards, whether they will or no, to receiue the effectes and proofes of so charitable courtesie. Besides all this, the Indians begin to wax shrewd lads, and to make no more so much account of glasses, pinnes, and such other spanish gifts: peraduenture bicause some body hath made them to tast this saying of <hi>Sophocles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sophoc. in Aiax.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <q>
               <l>Take heed for giftes of enimes,</l>
               <l>They are no gifts worthy of praise.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And albeit, all other causes wanted, is it possible that the possession of a thing so euill gotten should continue long? Thinke we that there is any Indian, in subiection of the Spaniards, which in his speach crieth not out a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand times a day,<note place="margin">Aristophanes in Pluto.</note> this sentence of <hi>Aristophanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>To serue a foolish master which hath no wit,</l>
               <l>Is a troublesome thing and full of despight.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Aristotle</hi> saith, that a countrie is possessed and helde by a tyrant in the same manner that mens bodies are with an agew.<note place="margin">Aristotle in his fist booke of Metaphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sickes. cap. 23.</note> What a number of sighes and grones, thinke wee do the wretched Americanes (so long tormented with that feauer of the Spanish crueltie) cast forth, which mount vp to the eares of him that holdeth the sterne of the matters of this world? Thinke we that Gods hand is shortened, so
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21569:21"/>as he cannot in dew time execute the threatninges which he hath vttered by the mouth of his prophet against these murtherers, robbers and wasters?<note place="margin">Esay. 33.</note> Where is the state in the worlde, be it neuer so flourishing, that can bee exempted from decay, and vtter ouerthrowe? Which is the wisedome and counsell, what the force, that can defend it, from the hande of the liuing God? Mischiefe runneth a pace, from house to house, sayth <hi>Euripides,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euripides in Electra.</note> in most richest and exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site wordes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Troubles and aduersities do fall vpon men so,</l>
               <l>As God will appoint, And windes be cast to and fro.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The same (and with much better reason) may be sayde of Monarchies also, wherein we may see from day to day,<note place="margin">Hesiodus de oper. &amp; dieb.</note> the accomplishment of this threatning, which is so wisely set downe by <hi>Hesiodus</hi> speaking of <hi>Iupiter,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>He pulleth downe the mightie ones from their wealth,</l>
               <l>Verie easily and againe, the abiect he doth exalt:</l>
               <l>It is he which doth correct them that are not sound,</l>
               <l>And the stout and wicked men breaketh down to ground.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which thing dooth take place specially then when the finnes, as well of the people, as of the Magistrate, in forceth God to breake his patience. The Mathematicians hold o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,<note place="margin">Vitellius, li. 4.</note> that the increasing of the greatnes of things, which are exceeding great, maketh them to seeme to come neere vnto our sight: notwithstanding that in very truth, they come nothing neere at all.<note place="margin">Theox. 129,</note> But the case standeth farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, where God is moued with mens sinnes: for the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21569:22"/>heaping of them vp one vpon an other, not only approch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but also preaceth them into the sight and presence of the liuing God, who oftentimes punisheth the people by the king, and the king by the people, whose iustice is not ruled by the same square that directeth the iudgements of men, and of common-weales. Wherein (according to the opinion of the Lawyers) <hi>Noxa caput sequitur, Penaltie pursu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the head.</hi> Thereof we haue a manifest and notable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>Abimelech</hi> king of <hi>Gerar,</hi> who in excusing of himselfe vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> vsed these wordes: what haue I done vnto thee?<note place="margin">Caius lib. 20. &amp; vltimo. D. de Noxal. Action. Genesis. 20.</note> and wherein haue I offended thee, that thou hast brought on me and on my kingdom this great sinne? Now if <hi>Abimelech</hi> do call adulterie a great sinne, what name shall we giue to that whereof no better description can be giuen than to liken it vnto the example set downe by <hi>Suetonius</hi> in the life of <hi>Claudius</hi> in the xxvi. chapter of his booke.<note place="margin">Suetonius.</note> And if any man thinke this speech to be ouer darke, let him but read that which is written by the Lawyer <hi>Paulus, lib.</hi> 39. vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the title, <hi>Si quis D. de ritu nuptiarum,</hi> concerning the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie of Mariage, and he shall vnderstand my meaning plaine ynough: but this is not all, for there are yet in this behalfe, other sorts of wickednesses, as much or more abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable than the other, which they thinke to keepe verie secret, as if the saying of the Poet <hi>Musaeus</hi> should not take place, as well in one age as in an other.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Oftentimes is sounded out in open streete,</l>
               <l>The wicked worke which men do thinke to hide.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now then, if we esteeme Gods iustice to be vnchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, let vs knowe, and be well assured, that God will visite so great and cursed kinds of wickednes, which may with more honestie than ease, be concealed: and shall (how long so euer he forslow it) make to feele his vengeance vnto the Spaniard and his king.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21569:22"/>
               <l>A cruell Tirant ouer whose leaud head,</l>
               <l>The wrath of God hanges readie to be spread.</l>
            </q>
            <p>To be short, the time will come ere long, and shall not stay, that this wicked Nation, which for these hundred yeares, hath made a trade of pilling and praying vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: shall be made a pray and bootie vnto other Nations. The time (I say) drawes neere, wherein eyther the Indians, or else the king of Spaines Lieutenantes themselves shall rebell against him, and shall become executors of Gods wrath against the couetousnesse and crueltie of their owne Nation.</p>
            <p>Now remaineth to be considered the third and last point of this discourse, that is to wit, whether of these two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being become our enimies, hath most meanes to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy vs: this point may well be ended, by reason of that which hath beene treated in the former article, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the meanes which eyther of those Nations haue to succor vs with all: yet notwithstanding such is the case, that if the Englishmen should happen to set foote in <hi>France,</hi> and specially in <hi>Gwyen,</hi> it would be so hard for vs to stay a great part of the Nobility and gentlemen from taking their part, as to burie the remembrance of the good turnes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, which their houses haue receiued heretofore at the handes of the kinges of <hi>Englande,</hi> especially considering that the Charters of the greatest houses of <hi>Guyen,</hi> are as manie witnesses, or rather as many authenticall recordes to prooue howe much they bee bound to remember the kinges of <hi>England.</hi> Moreouer, comming at hande with the Englishmen, euery one knoweth that they haue good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, large and deepe, and they which can not be dray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>On the contrarie part, according to the opinion of that great Captaine the Admirall of <hi>Chastillion,</hi> it will bee no lesse easie than expedient vnto vs, to ouer-come the Spaniardes, if wee warred vpon them as we ought, that is to say, if we would cut off the riuer at the spring head, by setting vpon thē at home in their owne countrie: which is a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21569:23"/>land very easie to be entred into, being both vnfurnished of strong Townes, and also which can not but very hardly be succored from <hi>Germanie.</hi> Whereas contrariwise, our armie should be backed by the countries of <hi>Languedocke,</hi> and <hi>Gas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyne,</hi> both of them well stored of victuals and men of war, in so much that that quarter may at this day be called in <hi>France,</hi> the storehouse of <hi>Mars.</hi> Therfore although I should proceede no further, and adde nothing else, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the causes heretofore set downe, being well consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, do conclude sufficiently of themselues, that to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, or to match in equalitie, the allyance with <hi>Spaine,</hi> to the allyance with <hi>England,</hi> is an open shewing of our selues to be vnnaturall and vnkinde to our allyes. It is (I say) a shewing of our selues to be blockish, and vnable to discerne the nature that matcheth iump with ours, from the nature that is cleane contrarie to it. It is (I say againe) a manifest setting and opposing of our selues against the benefite, and welfare of our countrie.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniardes</hi> (as we haue saide) be couetous, guilefull, proud, and rauenous. Shall we change then, the franke liberalitie, into a slauish and vnsatiable couetous nigardli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse? shall we change the generositie of the Lyon, into the malice of the Foxe? Shall we (I say) become of gentle, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogantes and disdamefull, and of milde and meeke, cruell and rauenous? Shall we so bereaue our selues of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues that haue purchased vs so great reputation thorough the whole worlde, as that there shall remaine no more vnto vs, but only the bare name of Frenchmen?</p>
            <p>And yet if we consider throughly the nature of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niarde, the miserable exchange whereof I speake will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more be noted as a manifest and sure recorde of our ouer great plyantnesse, in making so great account of that Nation, which after the manner of the iuie hath alwayes made those to fele the most pernitious effects of their most hurtfull malice which haue beene most straightly lynked vnto them.</p>
            <p>Now for as much as prayer is counted for a duetie of an honest man towardes his Countrie, I pray vnto God, O <hi>France,</hi> that thy preseruation and increase, may be a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21569:23"/>mirror of his goodnesse and wisedome, shining forth in the gouernement of the great states and kingdomes. And that to the same end, he may open thy eye lids, so as thou mayest haue the skill to discerne the poyson mingled with honnie, whereby they go about to set forwarde the ouerthrowe and vtter abolishment of thine honour and greatnesse.</p>
            <q>
               <l>All that hath a beginning, hath an end,</l>
               <l>Well that man that hath his time wel spent.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Tradutta &amp; scritta questa vera pruoua,</l>
               <l>Da Francesco Marquino, com' cosa nuoua.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Iddio salui la Regina Elizabetha,</l>
               <l>Ela doni lunga &amp; prospera vita.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>